Right? Let's be honest. Most people
don't set goals because they've
benefited from doing it before. They do
it because they're feeling bad. You look
at what you've achieved over the past
year and it's not what you wanted.
You're not happy with the progress. You
feel a bit behind in life. You're
frustrated that you don't feel any
closer to the life that you actually
want. So, you sit down and start
planning your goals to deal with that
feeling. And almost immediately, things
do feel different. You feel a sense of
relief. You feel a bit of excitement.
The future already seems like it's going
to be better. things feel more organized
and that frustration about the past year
starts to fade because you can see a way
out of it. Now, I know that at some
point in your life, you've planned goals
before. Even if you don't do it
regularly, you've definitely done it at
some point. And I know you know what I'm
talking about here, that feeling that
you get. And from a brain point of view,
it makes total sense because your brain
is constantly trying to reduce
uncertainty. So, the moment that you
define a future outcome, you create a
sense of order and that alone can
activate your reward system. Dopamine is
released, but not because you've made
progress, but because your brain now
believes that progress is possible. But
the problem for most traders is that the
goals they set in that moment aren't
actually going to get them where they
want to go. The way the goal is planned
means that at best, it ends up being
completely disconnected from what you
actually end up doing. And at worst, it
actually influences your behavior in the
wrong way and sabotages your progress.
So, in this video, I'm going to show you
how to plan goals that actually serve a
real purpose. Goals that don't just make
you feel better for a brief moment, to
make you feel less frustrated about the
previous year, but actually give you
structure, give you direction, and give
you a reliable way to achieve more
things. And obviously, our focus here is
going to be on trading, but the same
exact principles can apply to anything
else. Let's get you on track to
achieving more from this year than
you've ever ever achieved before. So,
first things first, what purpose do
goals really serve? Are they even
necessary?
Well, with the way that most people set
goals, nope. They don't serve much
purpose at all. They're more like a
glorified wish list. You get this
illusion of motivation for a moment
because imagining achieving the outcome
makes you feel good. Like if you set a
goal of I'm going to make a million
pounds from my trading this year. Sure,
you can picture what that would feel
like if you achieved it and that feels
exciting. But once you stop feeling
hyped from imagining that, you're left
with nothing that you can actually use.
And listen, I'm not saying that like I'm
somehow above it, like I'm judging you
from some moral high ground, because
I've set plenty of goals like that over
the years and they feel good. But we're
stopping that right now because a
properly designed goal is different. At
neurological level, a goal is a
coordination tool. Its job is to give
your brain direction so it can organize
behavior and filter information more
efficiently and more effectively. So
your executive systems, especially the
prefrontal cortex, prioritize, plan, and
keep your actions aligned over time
instead of constantly switching focus.
And when the objective is unclear, those
systems just burn energy trying to
decide what matters. And you experience
that as mental noise, second-guessing,
hesitation, mental friction for getting
things done, distractions, things like
that. But when the objective is clear,
it becomes a performance machine. It
becomes easier to plan, easier to ignore
distractions, and easier to execute,
which is something that I know a lot of
people struggle with. Goals also change
how motivation works. You know, a lot of
people get the wrong idea of what
motivation is. It's not about just
wanting it badly enough or hyping
yourself up by watching a load of
motivational videos. You may have even
noticed that recently I deleted all the
motivational videos I'd created years
ago, even though they had millions of
views and continues to get lots and lots
of views all the time because it's just
pointless. Instead, a big part of it
comes from dopamine systems that respond
to prediction and expectation. So when
your brain can see a believable path
forward, something that you actually
want, effort starts feeling worthwhile
because it's connected to something
real, not just hope, and that is driving
motivation to take the actions because
it's taking you closer and closer to
something you actually want. Goals can
also tighten behavioral control. The
prefrontal cortex works alongside deeper
action selection systems including
circuits in the basil ganglia to
regulate what you do next, what you
ignore, what impulses you suppress,
things like that. And a clear goal gives
those systems a way to filter. So
instead of reacting to whatever feels
urgent in the moment, having these sort
of emotional impulses, behavior becomes
a lot more directed. And finally, goals
make feedback from what you're doing and
from your environment actually usable
and useful. So your brain is constantly
comparing what's expected to happen with
what actually happens. And those gaps
drive learning. So when the goal is
clear, feedback from your actions
becomes something you can actually work
with rather than just being noise that
leads you nowhere. So you can think of
it this way. Your brain is built for
high performance. It might not feel like
it at times, but it is. When you get the
settings all wrong, it's not going to
function correctly, and this powerful
machine is going to struggle. But when
you set things up just right, it's off
to the races. You'll be able to do
things that right now you don't even
think it's possible to do because you've
never given yourself the proper chance
to until now. And that's the problem
that most traders have. They just don't
give their brain what it needs. and
instead they set these goals that lead
to these mechanisms not being able to
function in the right way. And when you
really sort of investigate these goals
and see where it is that people are
going wrong, they usually fall into at
least one of five failure categories.
I'm going to walk you through each of
those categories. And here's what I want
you to do. Leave me a comment below
letting me know which of these
categories you recognize from your own
trading goals, whether they're recent
ones or ones of the past. And maybe even
share your most ridiculous trading
related goal. sort of like a right of
passage because if you share it saying
it's ridiculous then you know you can
never go back to that way of thinking
again and we can all have a laugh about
it. Okay, so the first failure category
is controllability. Almost all the goals
that I see traders setting revolve
around things like profit targets,
return percentages, pip counts, or
number of trades. Sometimes it's
obvious, like I'll make 5% per month or
I'll make $100,000 from my trading this
year. And sometimes it's indirect and a
bit sneaky, like saying I'll get funded
by the end of March, which is basically
just a profit target with a deadline.
You're basically saying I'll make 10%
profit by March or something like that,
but it's just disguised as not being
that, but it still is a profit target.
Now, the problem with these goals isn't
that they're too over ambitious or
anything like that. I love people being
ambitious. I want you to be driven. But
that's not what the issue is here. The
issue is that all of these goals and
goals like these depend on variables
that you don't control. You can control
your actions, or at least I hope you
can. You can't control the markets, but
that also means you don't control how
many valid opportunities appear in a
given period of time. You can't control
when probabilities will play out in your
favor or not. You don't control
volatility or other market context. But
the truth is those factors determine
outcomes far more than your effort does,
especially over the short term. Sorry to
burst your bubble. So when a goal
depends on things outside your control,
it creates tension. Your brain detects a
gap between where you are and where you
think you should be. Like let's say for
example that your goal is to make 10% a
month, but there's one week left of the
month and you're still at break even.
What happens then? Well, your brain
starts looking for ways to close the gap
using the only things that you can
influence. So, you can't change the
markets in your favor, but you can
change your trade frequency. So, how
often you open trades, trade quantity,
your position size, trade management,
risk management, and that's when your
behavior is going to take a dive off a
cliff because you're going to start
forcing your trades, lowering your
standards, and convincing yourself that
an opportunity is good enough. if it's
close enough to being one. Increasing
your risk amount, holding on to losing
trades, doubling down, cutting
profitable trades too early or holding
on to them too long till they go against
you. Revenge trading. You get the idea.
And it's not because you suddenly became
a reckless or undisiplined person. It's
because you're just doing what you can
to achieve this goal. So, you're no
longer trading the markets. You're
trading your needs to make the goal
happen. And at that point, the goal
stops acting as a guide. and starts
becoming a problem. By the way, you've
probably noticed that I'm talking about
your brain as if it's somehow separate
to who you are. And that's obviously not
the case, but I'm doing it intentionally
because I want you to realize that a lot
of what happens in your brain is
non-concious. So, you're not consciously
controlling these things. You justify it
with the narrative after it's happened.
But the more you recognize that, the
more likely you'll be to take steps
proactively that make processes helpful
ones rather than self-sabotaging ones.
So these things are not under your
conscious control in the moment, but you
can take the steps like setting the
right goals that lead to the
non-concious actions being more helpful
than harmful. So onto the next failure
category, reinforcement. One of the main
ways the brain learns is through operant
conditioning, which basically means that
behavior is shaped by consequences. So
if something is followed by a reward,
the brain is more likely to repeat it.
If it's followed by punishment, it's
more likely to avoid it. And you can see
this in your childhood. If you touch a
hot pan and you get burned, then you
don't do it again. If you do something
that makes your parents laugh, then
you're likely to repeat it the same
thing over and over again until it stops
being funny and just ends up annoying
everyone, which is exactly what it was
like at Christmas for my niece and
nephews. But the problem with this
process when it comes to trading is that
it's not going to work out very well if
the thing you're judging about whether
you should do more or less of something
is the result of individual trades. You
know, I always rant at people who say
things to me like, "Oh, the great thing
about trading is that you get immediate
feedback about whether you were right or
wrong." No, you don't. That is absolute
bollocks and it's one of the beliefs
that [__] up so many traders. Trading
is probabilistic. Now, what that means
in practical terms is that you could
take an absolutely terrible trade, one
that has negative expectancy, which
means that if you kept taking that trade
again and again, you'd burn through your
bank account quicker than an ARS. You
could make all the mistakes in the
world, risk too much money, do all the
wrong things, and still walk away with a
profit. On the other hand, you could
have a great positive expectancy trade,
one that if you kept taking that type of
trade again and again and again, you're
going to make money over the long run.
you can make all the right decisions, do
everything perfectly, and still end the
day in a loss. That is the reality of
probabilities. Now, is that really
instant feedback about whether you were
right or wrong? No, it's not. Now, think
about what happens if your goals are
based on profit outcomes or returns or
things like that or if you're looking at
the profit from each trade as a sign of
progress towards some other goal that
you've set and therefore losses are a
setback, right? Then what that means is
that if a terrible trade makes you
money, your brain treats it as a
success. Dopamine is released, that
behavior that produced that result is
reinforced. Even if it was fundamentally
flawed, your brain doesn't care that it
was a bad trade, there was bad
decision-m, it just remembers, I did
that thing and I got paid. And over
time, you're training yourself to repeat
exactly the same actions that will
destroy your edge. Or if you execute the
trades well but lose money, your brain
will treat that as failure. Cortisol
will be released even though those
behaviors are the ones that would lead
you to long-term success if repeated
consistently. So the learning signals
get inverted. Instead of reinforcing
good trading, your goals reward luck and
punish competence. And once that pattern
sets in, you're no longer building
skill. you're conditioning yourself to
chase short-term relief and lucky
profits rather than developing a real
long-term edge. And that's why two
traders can do the exact same thing and
learn completely different lessons from
it. And this actually relates to the
third failure category, which is
feedback. And when I talk about
feedback, I don't just mean someone else
reviewing your trading and giving you
feedback. I mean what your brain is
using to judge whether something is
being done correctly or not and what
sort of progress you're making towards
achieving your goal. And this matters
because feedback is what drives learning
and course correction. And it's also
what keeps you engaged long enough to
actually improve and achieve your goal.
But the problem is that most trading
goals are planned in a way that doesn't
give you a real gauge of whether things
are being done right or not. And no way
of seeing progress other than by looking
at your profit and loss. So they haven't
defined a standard of correctness for
the actions and tasks or an appropriate
measure of progress for the overall
goal. But your brain is a prediction
machine and is constantly trying to
answer questions like am I getting
better? Is this working? Should I keep
doing this? So when your goal is
distant, vague or unrealistic, your
brain can't extract a clear signal to
know how it's doing or what needs to
change. It's just getting noise instead.
And that's obviously not going to be
very helpful. So, imagine you've just
started learning to trade today. It's
your very first day learning anything
about trading. And you've set your goal
to become a full-time profitable trader
by the end of the year. Like, it's a
pretty ridiculous goal. On a day-to-day
basis, or even a monthto-month, week-
toeek basis, what feedback is your brain
actually going to receive to know
whether you're getting closer to your
goal or not, and what you should do more
of or less of? It doesn't know. So, in
that case, attention gets scattered.
effort gets misallocated and you end up
reacting to whatever feels most urgent
or emotionally charged instead of what's
actually going to help moving forward to
achieving that goal. This is also where
reward prediction error becomes
problematic because when there's a big
gap between what you expected and what
you're getting, your brain registers
urgency. Your thinking starts to narrow
and short-term relief starts to matter a
lot more than long-term improvement. And
that estate triggers a cortisol
response. And high cortisol inhibits the
prefrontal cortex, the part responsible
for planning, impulse control, following
rules, all the good stuff. And at the
same time, control starts to shift
towards the amydala, which is built for
threat and immediate action. So in a
nutshell, what this means is that
biologically you become less capable of
trading well because you're less capable
of making the right sort of decisions,
the rational decisions, and more likely
to make the wrong decisions and do the
things that you're not meant to do. And
if you've ever looked back at a trade
and thought to yourself, "What on earth
was I thinking? That was really [__]
stupid." And yes, unfortunately, we've
all had those moments. Well, truth is,
you probably weren't thinking. your
prefrontal cortex was probably
effectively offline because you were
pushed into a stress state where good
decisions become near impossible. All
right. Then the fourth failure category
is believability.
You will not fully commit effort to a
goal that you don't genuinely believe
that you can achieve or to a plan that
you don't genuinely believe will get you
to that goal. And for most traders, that
belief is completely missing, even if
they won't admit it to themselves or
other people. You see, big goals feel
good to set because they let you imagine
the rewards if you achieve them. Like,
if you say, "I want to be a millionaire
for my trading by the end of the year,"
you can picture the lifestyle, the
freedom you'd have, the validation. But
if you haven't even traded profitably on
a live account yet, and you don't have
anywhere near the sort of capital that
you're going to need to achieve that
sort of goal, your brain is going to
know the goal just isn't realistic. You
know, wanting something isn't the same
as actually believing the thing. And
belief is what determines whether you're
going to maintain a high level of effort
and commitment even when things get
uncomfortable, when they get boring,
difficult, tedious, when distractions
come up, all of that sort of stuff. And
listen, you can dress it up however you
like. You can say that you're trying to
speak things into existence or some
other [__] like that that everyone
spends far too much time focused on
rather than actually doing things. But
some things just aren't going to be
believable to your nervous system. You
can convince yourself that you do
believe it, but deep down you're still
not going to. Like I could make it my
goal this year to run faster than Usain
Bolt. And I might visualize it and say
it over and over again to myself and
convince myself that I do believe it and
it still wouldn't produce any real
commitment from me because deep down I
still don't believe that it's
achievable. My brain is not treating
this as an achievable goal. So I
probably finished the year having made
no progress at all, let alone being
anywhere near as fast as him. When if I
had set a more reasonable goal, I
probably would have pushed myself a bit
more cuz I would have thought it's
achievable. But because the goal was too
big, it actually ended up sabotaging me.
I'm saying this like I've actually set
that as a goal. I haven't. I'm slow as
[__] I find it funny even just the idea
of me working towards that as a serious
goal. Like how would I decide that one?
Yeah. This year I want to be able to
just run really fast like why why why
would that ever come up? Even when the
goal itself is reasonable, not me being
faster than Usain Bolt, but something
that's a bit more reasonable. Then
believability can also break down due to
the plan itself. I mean, we can even
think about it logically. Like, if you
don't genuinely believe the plan you're
working on is the best way to achieve
the goal. What do you think's going to
happen? Like, imagine you're at work and
your boss says, "Here, I want you to do
these things cuz we're trying to achieve
this thing. I want you to put in your
full effort." And then you look through
the actions. You're like, "There's no
way that that's going to lead to this
goal." Are you really going to put in
your full effort, or are you going to
think that's probably a waste of my
time, or I could do things a slightly
different way that gets us there better
or sooner? So, what happens? You second
guess the actions. you start drifting.
You look for alternatives and that
reduces your level of commitment. And
the problem is a lot of this isn't
happening consciously. So you're not
consciously thinking, okay, so that's
the action I've set here, but there's a
best thing I could be doing, so I'm
going to work on that. Because if that
was the case, you would have a different
plan. Instead, it's happening
subconsciously. You just don't believe
in the steps that you got. So you end up
not following them. And it's because
most people spend almost no time
designing their plan properly or they'll
just feed their goal into chat GPT and
get the plan done for them with all
these fancy silly names that it comes up
with for the different phases and stuff.
But they never have that belief deep
down that this is the most optimal way
to spend your time and that if you take
these actions that follow this sequence
of tasks, your goal is inevitable. And
if you don't have that feeling, then you
could end up not doing anything at all.
And at that point, the goal isn't
guiding your behavior like it should be.
It's basically just a childish wish. And
that sounds harsh. But let's talk about
the fifth failure category, which is
progression. Humans suffer from a
wellocumented cognitive bias called the
planning fallacy. We systematically
underestimate how long things take to
do. And that applies just as much to
learning to trade, to achieving trading
goals, as it does to anything else. Most
traders want results now. They don't
want to wait for it. They want money,
freedom, relief from their frustrations
and their problems as quickly as
possible. And of course, everyone wants
that to an extent. Like if someone gave
you the option of having these amazing
things now or having to wait for them,
you'll take them now. But there's a
difference between knowing that's not
realistic and therefore being a bit more
patient about things and designing
everything to try and achieve that as
quickly as possible. And when urgency
starts driving how your goals are set,
then your development gets compressed
into an unrealistic timeline and you end
up chasing an outcome that's not
realistic rather than chasing the
progression towards it, which is what
you should be focusing on. And so
traders skip stages, they cut corners,
take shortcuts, overload themselves with
an unrealistic workload, and they expect
to reach their goals faster than what
realistic skill development actually
allows. So, they're trying to achieve an
impossible task, but they don't care.
They'll still push themselves and try
and achieve it anyway, even in the face
of a goal that even they can accept is
probably impossible. All because that
quote on Instagram told them that it's
only impossible until it's done. Or
actually, the one that makes me cringe
the most is this one. Impossible just
says I'm possible. [__] me. That one
belongs in the same category of pathetic
as people who still share minion memes
on Facebook. Anyway, let's get back on
track. Now, if you hadn't already
guessed, this mismatch between your
timeline and reality will have
consequences and not very good ones. The
first possible consequence is chronic
stress because when you're behind
schedule or you feel like you're behind
schedule, your brain interprets that as
a threat and it shifts into scarcity
mode. And at that point, learning shuts
down. So, instead of trying to improve,
you start trying to catch up or survive.
And I've heard this from traders for
years. It's one of the most common
things I hear from, especially from
younger men. They don't just feel behind
with their trading development. They
feel behind in life. They feel like
their peers, their friends or family are
all ahead of them, and they're getting
left behind. People are achieving
things, moving on, and they're still
stuck because they're focusing on their
trading. And that pressure either makes
them rush harder, which also leads to
negative consequences, or it drains
their motivation so much that it leads
to avoidance. And then you slowly start
avoiding the work that you're meant to
be doing because doing it reminds you
that you're not where you want to be
yet. The second consequence is even more
obvious and even more widespread. So
with trading, at some point down the
line, you're going to be risking real
money. That's the aim here. Right now,
if you rush your development, which
means that you don't develop correctly,
you don't just delay your progress, you
can actually make things a lot worse
because you'll end up making mistakes
that cost you money. So, you've actually
lost something as a result of that. It's
not just you gaining something at a
slower rate. You've actually lost
something. You can also damage your
confidence that is also losing
something. And you can create emotional
baggage that then has to be undone at a
later point in time, which takes a lot
of work. And that's difficult to do
because a lot of this becomes
conditioned responses which are a real
[__] to try and undo lace down the line
because a lot of the time you're not
even aware of them. They're unconscious
responses to a neutral stimuli. It's
like they're such a pain in the ass to
try and undo. They're very powerful
things. So all of this means that
instead of just accepting realistic
progression where you move forwards at a
slow and steady pace, you end up moving
backwards really quickly, your desire to
get ahead quickly has led to you going
backwards even quicker. And all because
you set an arbitrary deadline that
forced you to try and move faster than
skill acquisition realistically allows.
And let's be honest here, cuz I know
we're all thinking this, that part of
the problem is also that people just
can't be bothered to do the work. A
prolonged period of time developing a
skill, putting in the hours without
getting paid for it yet sounds like hell
to them. They're not willing to do it.
So, they just look for shortcuts to jump
straight to the part where they can make
money. Well, congratulations, you lazy
bastard. You just lost all your money
instead. And yes, I know I'm being a bit
harsh there, but if that's you, you need
someone to give you a reality check so
you can stop what you're doing before it
gets any worse. I say it because I care.
So, those are the five failure
categories. Now, the good thing about
laying them out like this is that they
don't just explain why your past goals
may have failed and why you maybe been
going backwards, but they also give us
criteria that good goals should satisfy.
So, now we've got a list of things that
we can make sure our goals tick the
boxes of. And that leads us to the
question, how do we design goals that
avoid these traps and actually lead to
us making progress, lead to us achieving
more than we would without them? Now, if
goals have never worked for you before,
it could be because you're asking one
goal to do five different jobs. So, the
first shift we're going to make is to
stop relying on a single goal to do
everything. Now, obviously, you'll set
different goals for different areas of
your life. You might have a fitness
goal, a work goal, a trading goal. I'm
not talking about that. I'm talking
about specifically the trading goal.
Rather than having one, we're going to
split it up because one goal can't
provide you with all the direction,
motivation, feedback, behavioral control
all at once that you need at different
phases along the way to achieve the
overall thing you're trying to achieve.
What you need instead is a hierarchy.
You know, I love a hierarchy. And this
is one that I call the performance
pyramid. We're going to split your goals
into three layers, each operating on a
different time horizon. So we've got the
mountain, the milestones, and the
stepping stones. The mountain is the
overarching direction. So this the thing
that you're working towards, the big
goal, however long it takes to get
there. Then the milestones are the
sequence of outcomes that need to be
achieved along the way to reach that
mountain. And the stepping stones are
the daily or weekly actions that move
you from one milestone to the next. So
allow you to achieve each of those
milestones. Listen, when all of this is
put together correctly, actual magic
happens. So the stepping stones are
planned well enough that if you execute
them consistently, the milestones become
unavoidable. And when milestones are
sequenced correctly, achieving them
means that conquering the mountain is
inevitable. Think about what that means.
Just by planning things correctly, you
can achieve the greatest success of your
life and operate as a high performance
machine just by completing a simple
to-do list each day. Because that's the
thing that most people don't realize,
achieving amazing things, developing
amazing skills. It's not about oneoff
moments of glory. It's basically just a
sequence of daily to-do lists being
completed consistently one after
another, day after day. Yeah, not
exactly the Hollywood moment. It's not
quite a rocky montage, but planning
things in this way means that achieving
that mountain goal stops being a matter
of hope. It's no longer a wish. It
becomes a matter of time. And this is
how we fix the believability and
progression issues right off the bat.
So, let's start at the top with the
mountain. This is the long-term
direction that you're moving your life
in. It's what you're trying to build,
become, or commit to achieving. And the
strongest mountain goals are connected
to a purpose, to a genuine why. But I
know that can sometimes feel a bit vague
or people struggle to figure out what
their purpose is. So instead, just think
of this as a multi-year direction that
you genuinely care about going in.
Something that if you were living it
right now, you would feel like you're
moving towards the life that you want.
Now, there's a really important rule
that you should stick to. You should not
put a deadline on your mountain goal.
Instead, you should think of this goal
as something that you so badly want to
achieve that you're willing to do
whatever it takes and keep working at it
for as long as it takes to get there.
And if we think about with trading, for
example, you simply can't know in
advance how long it's going to take to
develop the sort of competence and skill
that you're going to need. So any
deadline that you set is going to be
arbitrary. And arbitrary deadlines are
exactly what triggers the pressure and
short-term decision-m that we discussed
earlier that creates a problem. Instead,
the mountain serves two functions. And
actually, it does a lot more than that,
but there are two that I want to bring
your attention to. So, neurologically,
it provides tonic dopamine, that
background motivation that keeps you
pushing on even when things become
repetitive, tedious, or difficult. And
it engages the reticular activating
system which directs your attention. It
helps your brain decide what deserves
your focus and what doesn't. So in other
words, the mountain doesn't tell you
what to do today or tomorrow. It just
keeps you pointed in the right direction
long enough for the work to start to
compound to help you achieve the goal.
And I always find a good example of this
is something outside of trading and it's
medical research. So you always hear
these stories about people who watched a
loved one suffering from a disease or an
illness and so they decided to dedicate
their life to finding a cure for it and
they can't really set a deadline for
that, can they? They don't know when a
cure will suddenly be available. They
can't jump straight to the outcome. What
they can do is commit to the overall
direction. And that direction filters
everything else for them. What subjects
they study at high school, college, the
right degree that they apply for, what
they need to get to get into the right
university, the research roles that they
apply for, the funding they need to get,
projects they go through, testing,
trials. And along the way, there are
going to be all kinds of different
things that will pull them in different
directions, opportunities, people,
information, but their mountain will
always act as that filter to help them
to decide what's going to contribute to
reaching that goal or not. So, they end
up, of course, sometimes making
mistakes, but much less distracted and
much less pulled in different directions
because they have, to use the cliche, a
northstar. Right? Listen, if you haven't
been giving this your full attention so
far, cuz you've also been scrolling
social media, checking the comments,
maybe even liking and subscribing and
checking the link in the description,
hint hint, then I at least want you to
pay attention for this next bit, cuz
it's time for a really important reality
check that I know for sure a lot of
people watching this video desperately,
desperately need. So, here's the thing.
If your mountain goal, your overall goal
is purely related to exttrinsic
motivation, so money, status,
recognition, material possessions, that
kind of thing, then trading might not be
the right vehicle to reach it. There are
alternatives. Because here's the thing.
If money is the only reason you're here,
it's the only reason you're learning to
trade and looking to set a trading goal
because you think that it's going to
help you to achieve that, then the
moment that trading becomes difficult,
slow, stressful, boring, repetitive,
which by the way, it inevitably will at
some point, you'll start looking for
something easier. Or when another
opportunity comes up that seems like
it'll be a quicker and easier way to
reach those things, basically shiny
object syndrome, you'll be gone. I've
seen it time and time again to the point
that when someone joins us, I can tell
whether they're likely to stick it out
or if they're going to be one of those
people that are just motivated by money
and will disappear. And the problem is
if that is you, if at some point you're
going to move on to the next thing that
seems like it's going to get you there
in a more straightforward way, all of
the time, money, and effort that you've
put into learning to trade up until that
point is a complete waste. So, I'm
saying this to you now so that you can
be honest with yourself and save
yourself all of that waste because
social media has made things so much
worse. You see people posting these
flashy trading lifestyles acting like
they barely even have to work anymore.
They never feel any stress. And it
creates this illusion, this idea that
successful trading is relaxed. It's
easy. It's glamorous. But that's
marketing. That's not reality. The
online trading space is full of liars.
And I say this as someone who has
achieved the flashy cars, the holidays,
the properties long before I ever posted
anything trading related online or
taught anyone. It genuinely came from my
trading, which I think not many people
in the trading industry can honestly
say. But the reason I say all of this is
because I also know exactly what it took
to get to that point and what I've had
to deal with while having those things.
I started learning to trade around 2002,
and it wasn't until 2012, 10 years
later, that I'd made enough money from
my trading that I could leave my career
in banking and trade full-time. Now,
that's 10 years of learning, testing,
failing, long hours, stress, without any
reward, without even being paid for it
until the last few years of that period.
And even then, when I started making
more money for my trading, I've still
had to work long hours. I've still had
to be meticulous with my preparation
each and every day, be disciplined, not
only with what I do in the markets, but
also in how I live my life. And there's
been a lot of stress that's come from
trading with serious capital, especially
when it's included money from other
people and all kinds of issues that came
up from banking processes and various
other things like that. I've had to make
sacrifices in relationships, social
life, my health at certain times. And do
you know what's funny? After making all
of those sacrifices, and I've talked
about this on the channel before,
eventually I realized that all of those
things, the luxuries, whatever you want
to call it, didn't fulfill me anyway.
What I actually enjoyed was the work,
the process, the challenge. That
identity became the real asset. And
that's why I still work harder than what
I see most people doing who are trying
to succeed at this. And I've already
done a lot of the things that people are
trying to do. But I only got the success
because of what I was willing to do, the
skills that I developed, that I was
willing to spend that time developing,
and the habits that I had formed. So,
going back to what I said before, what
you see on social media makes it seem
like trading is some sort of cheat code
for life. But trading is not a cheat
code. It's a complex skill. And skills,
especially complex skills, are annoying
because they take so much time and work
to develop. Now, I'm not saying all of
this to be a downer or to put you off.
I'm saying it because it's so important
that you're completely honest with
yourself and that you understand what's
real, what is reality here. So before
you plan out your goals around trading,
be honest with yourself. You're not
working towards the rewards. You're
working towards becoming the person who
can earn those rewards and doing what
that sort of person does consistently,
not as a one-off, but consistently. And
that path isn't glamorous. It isn't
easy. It isn't what social media sells
you because most people selling the
lifestyle haven't achieved it by
trading. So, make sure your mountain
goal is something you genuinely want in
full, not just the highlight reel, the
full picture, good and bad. Because the
clearer that direction is, the more
useful it becomes as a filter for
everything else. Okay, that's the end of
my rant. I seem to fit a rant into every
video these days. Do you know why it is?
is that I've seen what's real and I've
seen what everyone sort of pushes as
what trading can do and I've seen what
it does to people's expectations and how
it throws people off course and it's so
frustrating to watch this happening and
I'm just one voice out here saying this
and it's getting sort of drowned out by
all these people saying something
different and there's a reason that so
many people end up throwing their life
away by getting involved in trading in a
way that's never going to lead them to
success. So, I will keep on having rants
about things and maybe I'll start
getting through to people one by one.
Who knows? But anyway, I said end of
rant and I've gone and ranted a little
bit more. So, let's get back on track.
So, once you've decided the mountain,
the next step is to reverse engineer it
so that we can come up with milestones
and stepping stones. So, milestones are
sort of like a series of projects. They
form the sequence that moves you from
where you are now towards that long-term
direction, that long-term goal. And to
plan them properly, you need to start
with an honest assessment of your
current situation and diagnose what's
missing. Okay? So, you know where you're
trying to get to. Now, you need to know
where you are now. And that gap between
those two points is filled with specific
capabilities and things that need to be
achieved or developed. Now, milestones
organize those capabilities into the
right order, an order that makes sense.
So, you only move forward once something
has actually been built, achieved,
developed. you're doing things in the
right order. You're not wasting time on
things that don't need to be done or
that should come later because a lot of
traders jump straight ahead to, you
know, the the more interesting stuff
before laying the right foundations to
get them there. Obviously, you're not
necessarily going to know every single
step in advance because you haven't
achieved that goal yet. So you don't
necessarily know every single milestone
and that's fine unless you have someone
guiding you who's already achieved it
before and can lay out that sort of
blueprint for you like the duo trader
development program where it's literally
planned in that way. But what matters
more is being able to identify the broad
stages and then you can refine it as you
go along. So for example, if your
mounting goal is to generate a side
income from trading a funded trading
account, then you already know that one
of the final milestones is going to be
securing that funding. So before that,
you have a step where you need to be
prepared for that funding process, which
is going to be very different to your
regular trading. So maybe you need to go
through scenario training and various
things that are going to set you up for
that process. But going through that
only makes sense if you can already see
that you're profitable. you've got
evidence of that in a reliable
consistent way with a large enough
sample size because otherwise why go for
funding if you haven't got the proof
that you actually are going to benefit
from it. So then before that there are
going to be certain skills that need to
be developed and so on and so on.
Getting that sequence right really
matters. So not only having the right
milestones but in the right order that
really matters. Like think back to the
believability problem we talked about
earlier. for this plan to really work
for you, you need to be able to look at
that milestone path, that sequence, and
think to yourself, yeah, if I complete
those milestones in that order, then the
outcome of all of this will mean that
achieving that mountain is inevitable.
It's unavoidable, and that's going to
give you the drive to actually complete
them and to work hard at this. But
unfortunately, that's just not going to
be possible for like 99% of traders for
two main reasons. So, first of all, most
traders have absolutely no idea what the
actual skills are that you need to
develop if you want to succeed at this
because what everyone tells you that you
should focus on and what everyone ends
up focusing on is usually not right and
it will usually lead to you relying on
luck without realizing it. Things like
learning to follow a strategy, learning
to spot setups, those things are not
really developing skills and it's not
going to lead you to achieving your goal
in a reliable way. And secondly, most
traders don't have a model that makes
their progress inevitable. Where the
more effort you put in, the more you do,
the more direct feedback you get that
leads to specific improvements that
leads to you doing things better that
goes round and round in a flywheel
effect. Because to achieve something
like that where your progress becomes
more reliable, your trading needs to be
based on a complete logical model, which
is something that most traders just
don't have. So if you want to understand
the actual skills that you need to
develop and the logical framework that
you need to follow if you want to make
progress towards your goals, something
reliable, check out the link in the
description box and you can get guidance
on all of this for free. I will teach
you it all. Now
must be based on things that you fully
control. If you're already making money
from your trading and you want to make
more, you want to increase your
profitability, setting a milestone of
something like increase my returns is
not going to help because you can't
control your returns like we talked
about earlier. What you can control is
the underlying behavior or skill that
leads to that. This is where the
difference between lag measures and lead
measures comes into things. So lag
measures are outcomes, things like
profit, funded status. by the time you
see them, they've already happened.
They're not going to be very helpful.
Whereas lead measures are predictive.
They're the behaviors that make those
outcomes more likely. So milestones
should be built around lead measures.
And this ties directly into the concept
of competency and self-efficacy. You
know, competence leads to more
confidence. You need to believe in your
ability to succeed. That's what
self-efficacy is all about. So you don't
build self-efficacy through lucky
streaks. You build it by repeatedly
proving that you can execute a skill. So
if you're a complete beginner,
milestones shouldn't be about market
performance because that's irrelevant.
They should be about executing specific
skills correctly without mistakes or
building specific knowledge. Or if
you've already been trading for a while
and you're certain that you have
developed the right skills in the right
way, then a milestone might be to focus
on improving your probability estimates,
the accuracy of them. And you can do
that by following a calibration process
where you make forecasts, collect data
on those forecasts, and when you've
built up a large enough sample size, you
can analyze the data to find the issues
and inaccuracies over a meaningful
sample so that you can make the right
adjustments so that in future your
probability estimates are more accurate.
Now, these are capability based goals.
They're concrete. They're falsifiable.
You either achieved them or you didn't.
And when you complete a capability
milestone, your brain receives the right
kind of reward signal. It's not relief.
It's not luck based. It's real evidence.
I committed to achieving something
specific and I delivered. And that
feedback builds confidence. It
stabilizes your motivation and makes
your continued progress psychologically
more sustainable. Now, just before we
come on to the third layer, the stepping
stones, I want to make a recommendation
to you. So, a little while ago, I
released a video about a process that we
go through with our members that's led
some amazing progress. Something we call
the monthly transformation cycle. And
really, all it is is a framework that
you can follow for planning and
following the milestones and stepping
stones on a regular basis with clear
measures of progress and indications of
when the thing has been completed. when
you've achieved the goal. I'd really
recommend checking that out so that you
have the complete template for all of
these, the milestones and the stepping
stones. So, I'll link the video on
screen up there now, but you can wait
till the end. It'll be in the end card
as well. So, the third layer, the
stepping stones are the foundation. This
is where the goals stop being conceptual
and start being practical, behavioral.
The time horizon is very short, so daily
to weekly. And these are the actions
that if repeated make achieving the
milestones inevitable. And this layer
actually ties in closely to what we know
about the flow state. How to achieve a
flow state. Because flow researchers
like the godfather Mihi Chicken Mihihi
showed that one of the criteria for
entering a flow state is having clear
goals. And that's exactly what stepping
stones are really. They're just a set of
clear goals. Which means that they're
going to make it much more likely for
you to reach higher levels of
performance. Whether that's you know
completing daily development tasks or
doing things in the markets they also
create a game within the game where your
success is defined by your execution of
the stepping stones rather than just
your P&L on the markets. So it's
something you can win at every day if
you commit and focus regardless of what
the market's doing. Now for stepping
stones to work they must be binary. So
it's got to be something where you
either did it or you didn't do it. And
they must be small enough that you can
do them even on a bad day when you've
got no energy, you can't be bothered,
it's small enough that you could just
get started and get it done. So for
example, if your milestone is improving
the accuracy of your probability
estimates, then you know that you need
to build a large enough sample size of
your forecasts so that you can actually
go through calibration and come up with
meaningful conclusions. So a stepping
stone might be completing 10 forecasts
per day in a simulator. So whether the
forecasts are good or bad doesn't
matter. The win condition for that is
just completion of the 10 forecasts. Or
if you want to make it even smaller, it
could be one forecast. But then
obviously it's going to take a lot more
days to build up the large sample size.
But maybe just by completing one, you
end up doing more of them. But even if
you just get one forecast done, that's a
win. Okay, that's a success for that
day. You see, by separating execution
from performance, you reduce cognitive
load. And you also stop waking up in the
morning and wondering what you should
work on because instead you just need to
run that process. And over time that
consistency becomes reinforcing because
you're doing the work that actually
builds skill. Now there is one enemy
that derails this layer more than
anything else and that's boredom. Most
impulsive traits don't come from panic.
They come from restlessness and the need
for stimulation. And the same thing
applies to distractions that can derail
your development. It's really easy to
give into those moments if you're not
actively trying to fight against them.
You know, your default action will be to
get distracted. So, you need to have a
plan built into these stepping stones
that avoids this. And it's got to be a
combination of two things. A stop doing
list and if then rules. So, research
shows that when we're trying to solve
something, we default to additive
solutions and completely ignore
subtractive solutions. But I guarantee
for most people watching this video, the
things that will disrupt your progress
the most aren't the things that you're
not currently doing. It's the things
that you currently are doing that you
need to stop, the things that you need
to subtract, not the things you need to
add. So having a stop doing list or a
daily code of conduct is going to help
with this. But it's really only going to
work if you have the second thing, which
is if then statements. So first of all,
you need to recognize what your triggers
are for the disruptive behaviors. And
then you could think about a plan to
offset them in some way. So it'll be
like if X starts happening, then I'll do
Y. If I start getting mentally drained
and feel like I want to scroll on social
media, I'll go for a walk without my
phone for 10 minutes and then come back
to work after that. If I feel like I'm
rushing into a trade after I've had a
loss, then I'll explain my thought
process out loud, record it in my voice
notes so that I can switch more to my
conscious processing. And basically by
deciding all of this ahead of time, you
remove that ability to negotiate with
yourself in the moment because you could
be really convincing. Instead, you move
the decision into the planning system.
So when that particular moment comes up,
you don't enter negotiation with
yourself. It's just like running a
script. You go into autopilot with it
and get over that particular thing. Now,
going back to the stepping stones and
milestones, it's really important that
you track something that's an
appropriate measure for the thing that
you're working on at that particular
point in time. Your attention is limited
and if you track the wrong things, your
behavior will start to drift, even if
the plan itself looks good. So, you
don't want to be tracking your daily P&L
as a success metric. You don't want to
be labeling weeks as a good or bad week
based on how much money you made in the
markets. You don't want to do that. And
you don't want to be changing your
milestones midway through them just
because your progress towards it is
making you feel uncomfortable. Instead,
track whether you completed your
stepping stones, sort of like a daily or
weekly scorecard on your execution, and
the specific measures that you've set
out for each milestone. So, the thing
that's showing you whether you're making
progress or whether you've achieved the
thing you're trying to develop. One
final warning though, even a perfectly
planned goal, goal system, let's call
it, can still be undermined by your
environment. So if you're sleepdeprived,
over stimulated, constantly checking the
charts all the time, trading with a
chaotic routine or in a chaotic area
with loads of distractions, your brain
is going to default to threats and
impulse systems. You know, goals don't
override physiology. They have to be
designed around it. And if your
physiology is working against you, then
psychology isn't going to save you from
it. And finally, there's sort of like a
wrapper around all of this, which
something I touched upon a bit earlier,
and that is identity. And this is
something I will be doing a whole video
about at some point because it's a
fascinating topic, but also because I
think it's one of the main reasons that
traders still end up failing even once
they've developed a really good level of
skill. It comes down to identity. But
for now, let me just give you a few
points that I want you to consider. So,
here's the thing. You don't get the
rewards from trading unless you become
the type of person who can consistently
produce them. I'm not talking about the
one-off profits by luck. I'm talking
about doing it based on skill. You're
not going to do that unless you become
that sort of person. If your self-image
doesn't support the right behaviors, the
whole thing collapses. The whole
process, your system, whatever. Humans
have a strong drive for internal
consistency. So, we tend to act in ways
that reinforce who we believe we are.
And once an identity forms, behavior
follows it automatically. But the
problem for most traders is that firstly
they're trying to adopt the wrong
identity and secondly they've already
developed the wrong identity. So it's
like a double whammy. When I say you're
trying to adopt the wrong identity, I
mean thinking that you need to build the
identity of I am a profitable trader or
I am someone who makes money in the
markets like working towards that being
your identity. But that sort of identity
is really fragile. Firstly, it doesn't
actually point to any real behavior.
Secondly, what happens when you have a
losing period? It's going to threaten
the identity and your behavior will
start becoming defensive. So instead,
process identities will work much
better. So your identity needs to be
built around things like I am detail
oriented. I am meticulous. If I say I'm
going to do something, I do it. I manage
risk consistently. I prepare properly
regardless of outcomes. and obviously
many other specific things related to
your trading approach that reinforces
the the right behaviors, the things that
are going to lead you to actually
succeeding. So the thing about those
statements and that type of identity is
that it holds up even during draw downs
or difficult periods. In fact, in
difficult periods, that's when those
statements become reinforced even more
because a losing month is going to
become even more evidence that you're
disciplined and not necessarily proof
that you're failing, which is how most
people see it because they think they're
trying to build the identity of I am a
consistently profitable trader. And all
of this matters because identity isn't
built through intention. It's built
through evidence. So these things are
either reinforcing the identity you want
or they're not. And this then relates to
the second point I made, which is that
most people watching this video right
now have probably already developed the
wrong identity. And this comes in so
many different ways. But a lot of you
deep down have the identity of a failure
or that good things can't happen to you.
Success is for other people but not for
you. I'm not talking about that you
think you're a failure consciously, but
deep down you think that you're not
going to succeed at this. When you start
doing something, you have this sort of
feeling in the back of your mind that
you're not actually going. I wasn't
doing six seven and you have this
feeling in the back of your mind that
you're not going to get to that end
goal. I shouldn't have said that. So,
obviously, this means that no matter how
much effort you put in, you feel like
it's going to lead you nowhere. So, what
ends up happening? Of course, you're
going to halfass things and not really
put in your full effort because you
don't believe it's worth it. So, it
becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy. And
then that becomes evidence that
reinforces the identity. And this
happens on a subconscious level. I'm not
saying you're aware of it all. Likewise,
a lot of people have the identity of
someone who doesn't do the things that
they say they will. So when you have a
task list, like your stepping stones,
you don't end up doing it. So what
happens is over time you lose trust in
yourself to the point where you'll write
down a list of things to do and not even
trust that you're actually going to
complete them. So that means that your
very first step is to start rebuilding
that trust with yourself. And you could
do that just by completing the things
that are on your list. It's like what
James Clear talks about. He says that
every action you take is a vote for the
type of person you're becoming. And over
time, those votes start to add up. Right
now, most traders are voting for being a
gambler and an addict with how they
approach their trading. So, think of it
this way. If you have a goal that you
desperately want and it's in your
control and then you have a plan that
you believe will inevitably get you to
that goal if you follow it, you then
just need to become the type of person
who completes the stepping stones each
and every day and you will achieve that
goal. So you need to start trusting in
yourself and believing that you are that
person and at that point the goal
becomes inevitable.
But this won't happen if you make the
mistake that everyone seems to make and
overestimate how much you can get done
each day. So keep your stepping stones
realistic and track what you do complete
or what you don't complete each day. And
don't think of it as like an all or
nothing. You know, it doesn't mean if
you've sort of missed one day that you
need to scrap the whole thing. Just
track it. And if you realize that you
can actually do more than what you're
doing, slowly add more tasks each day.
And if you realize it's too much, scale
it back a bit. But don't turn your
stepping stones into this massive,
unrealistic, unsustainable to-do list
where you can maybe complete it one or
two days, but there's no way you can
keep it up over the long run. Because
then what ends up happening is that it's
a matter of time before you don't
complete it. And then that's a vote for
the wrong identity. And eventually, I've
seen it so many times with different
people, you'll just drift away from it
and you'll stop following a structured
plan at all. And then you'll stop
believing that you can follow a
structured plan. And at that point, you
can just kiss sweet goodbye to ever
achieving your goals, unless you're
going to achieve them by luck, which is
not really going to be effective.
Anyway, as I said before, there's so
much more we could talk about with this
topic, and there's so much brilliant
academic research that will be so
helpful for your development as a
trader, but this video will get even
longer and even more out of hand if we
dig into that now. So, we'll revisit
another time in a separate video. And
once again, if you want to know what
skills you really need to develop and
the logical model that ties it all
together so that you can make reliable
progress, check out that link in the
description box. You'll quickly realize
that most of the stuff that traders are
told they need to focus on is a load of
[__] And if you want to dig deeper into
how to plan the milestones and the
stepping stones, including how to set
appropriate measures, feedback, and all
of that good stuff, on screen you'll see
the video I mentioned earlier, and
there's a template there that you can
follow as well. If you made it all the
way to the end, you better go and smash
it now. Don't let yourself down anymore.
Thanks for watching.